E3DA Unit, Bruno Kessler Foundation, Via Sommarive 18, 38123 Povo, TN, Italy

□ (+39) 320 012 6523 | ☑ rajeev.piyare@hotmail.com | 🏕 www.rajeevpiyare.com | 🛅 rajeevpiyare | 🧐 piyare\_raj | 📂 Rajeev Piyare

## Research Interests

My research interests lie in the field of energy-efficient decentralized and distributed systems, with an emphasis on energy-harvesting and radio-triggering techniques for cyber-physical systems. Specifically, my current work is focused on the following areas:

- Developing efficient wake-up radio MAC/routing protocols for energy constrained networked embedded systems, mainly for Wireless Sensor and Actuator Networks.
- Understanding the dynamics of complex systems through mathematical modeling and simulation-based techniques. The primary aim is to gain insights that can assist to design better energy-efficient wireless systems for the IoT.

## **Education**

University of Trento Trento, Italy

Ph.D. Candidate in Computer Science and Telecommunication

November 2014 - April 2019

- Thesis Title: Wake-up Radio based Approach to Low-Power and Low-Latency Communication in the Internet of Things
- · Advisor: Dr. Amy Lynn Murphy

**Mokpo National University** 

Jeonnam, South Korea

Masters in Engineering August 2012 - June 2014

- Thesis Title: Human Activity and Context Recognition Using Smartphone Sensors: An Online Approach
- · Advisor: Prof: Seong Ro Lee

**University of The South Pacific** 

Suva, Fiji

POSTGRADUATE DIPLOMA IN ELECTRONIC ENGINEERING

August 2009 - April 2011

#### **University of The South Pacific**

Suva, Fiji

BACHELOR OF ENGINEERING TECHNOLOGY IN ELECTRICAL AND ELECTRONIC ENGINEERING

February 2006 - December 2008

# Work & Research Experience

#### **Bruno Kessler Foundation (E3DA Unit)**

Trento, Italy

RESEARCHER IN THE INTERNET OF THINGS AND SENSOR NETWORKS

November 2014 - Present

- Development of a software stack for sensing and communication over ultra-low- power wake-up radios for short- and long-range networking.
- Development of energy efficient MAC and routing protocols for the wake-up radio-based systems.
- Development and integration of wake-up radio testbed.
- Development of mathematical models and simulation techniques for assessing and designing reliable and energy-efficient battery powered wireless systems.
- Mentored and supervised an undergraduate in LoRa and NB-IoT research project over 5 months.
- Maintenance and update of SoleLab, a 50-node WSN Testbed deployed in the facility.
- Deliverables: 2 journal publications, 4 international conferences.

#### Swiss Federal Institute of Technology (ETH)

Zürich, Switzerland

VISITING SCHOLAR AT IIS, LABORATORY OF PROF. LUCA BENINI

September 2017 - May 2018

- Design of a multi-radio multi-sensor platform comprising of LoRa and a wake-up receiver.
- Implementation of an On-demand TDMA communication protocol for improving both the energy efficiency and the latency of standard LoRa networks.
- Performance evaluation of the On-demand TDMA system in an indoor testbed under realistic network conditions, dynamics, and interference.
- Porting of ContikiOS for embedded networking with SX1276 LoRa chip and MSP430FR5969 platforms.
- Deliverables: 1 journal publication, 2 international conferences.

 SpazioDati
 Trento, Italy

 GRANT REVIEW PANEL MEMBER
 10th - 28th April 2017

- Project: United Nations Data for Climate Action Challenge (D4CA)
- Reviewing 50 grant applications towards solving global climate issues with the Big Data

FEBRUARY 3, 2019 RAJEEV PIYARE · CURRICULUM VITAE

**University of Trento** Trento, Italy

TEACHING ASSISTANT - LABORATORY OF WIRELESS SENSOR NETWORKS

- September 2015 February 2017 • Developing lab instructions and course materials for the lab sessions.
- Instructed lab sessions that involved programming wireless sensor nodes (Tmote Sky/ Zolertia Z1) using ContikiOS and TinyOS for sensing and control.
- Assessment and grading of student projects for the course.

Fiji National University Suva, Fiii

LECTURER IN ELECTRONICS, COLLEGE OF ENGINEERING SCIENCE & TECHNOLOGY (CEST)

- April 2009 October 2014
- Plan, prepare, and deliver lectures for Engineering Mathematics (MTH410) and Circuit Analysis (EED501) for Diploma in Electrical & Electronic Engineering and later degree levels.
- · Student project management and lab supervision.
- Preparation and assessment of student exams and projects for the courses.
- Carrying out administrative work related to the course and the program.
- · Engagement in training and professional development opportunities required by the faculty for enhancing research and teaching skills.
- Industrial collaboration, R&D.

# **Honors & Awards**

2017	<b>Student travel grant</b> , to attend/present at 42nd IEEE Conference on Local Computer Networks	Singapore
2014	Scholarship recipient, University of Trento for Ph.D. research	Trento, Italy
2012	Scholarship recipient, Woojung Education and Culture Foundation	Seoul, South Korea
2012	Scholarship recipient, Global IT Talent Support Program for Masters research	Seoul, South Korea
2006	Scholarship recipient, Fiji Multi-Ethnic Affairs for Bachelors Degree	Suva, Fiji

## **Publications**

### **Journal Papers**

- R.Piyare, A.L.Murphy, M.Magno and L.Benini, "On-Demand LoRa: Asynchronous TDMA for Energy Efficient and Low Latency Communication in IoT," MDPI Sensors, vol.18, no.11, pp.3718-3739, November, 2018. (Impact Factor: 2.475)
- R.Piyare, A.L.Murphy, C.Kiraly, P.Tosato and D.Brunelli, "Ultra Low Power Wake-Up Radios: A Hardware and Networking Survey," IEEE Communications Surveys & Tutorials, vol.19, no.4, pp.2117-2157, Fourthquarter 2017. (Impact Factor: 17.188)
- R.Piyare and S.R.Lee, "Activity Recognition of Workers and Passengers onboard Ships Using Multimodal Sensors in a Smartphone," The Journal of Korea Information and Communications Society, vol.39, Issue 9, pp.811-819, 2014.
- R.Piyare and S.R.Lee, "Towards Internet of Things (IOTs): Integration of Wireless Sensor Network to Cloud Services for Data Collection and Sharing," International Journal of Computer Networks and Communications, vol.5, No.5, September, 2013.
- R.Piyare, "Internet of Things: Ubiquitous Home Control and Monitoring System using Android based Smart Phone," International Journal of Internet of Things, vol.2, pp.5-11, 2013.
- R.Piyare and S.R.Lee," Performance Analysis of Xbee ZB Module Based Wireless Sensor Networks," International Journal of Scientific and Engineering Research, vol.4, pp.1615-1621, 2013.

### **Peer Reviewed Conference and Workshop Papers**

- R.Piyare, A.L. Murphy, M.Magno and L.Benini, "KRATOS: An Open Source Hardware-Software Platform for Rapid Research in LPWANs," In Proceedings of Wireless and Mobile Computing, Networking and Communications (WiMob), IEEE 14th International Conference on., 15th-17th October, Cyprus, 2018.
- R.Piyare, A.L. Murphy, M.Magno and L.Benini, "On-Demand TDMA for Energy Efficient Data Collection with LoRa and Wake-up Receiver," In Proceedings of Wireless and Mobile Computing, Networking and Communications (WiMob), IEEE 14th International Conference on., 15th-17th October, Cyprus, 2018.
- R.Piyare, A.L. Murphy, P.Tosato and D.Brunelli, "Plug into a Plant: Using a Plant Microbial Fuel Cell and a Wake-up Radio for an Energy Neutral Sensing System," In Proceedings of the Local Computer Networks Workshops (LCN Workshops), IEEE 42nd Conference on., 9th-12th October, Singapore, 2017.
- R.Piyare, T. Istomin and A. Murphy, "WaCo: A Wake-Up Radio COOJA Extension for Simulating Ultra Low Power Radios," In Proceedings of the 14th ACM International Conference on Embedded Wireless Systems and Networks (EWSN), 20th-22nd February, Uppsala, Sweden, 2017.
- R.Piyare and S.R.Lee, "Dynamic Activity Recognition using Smartphone Sensor Data," In Proceedings of International Electronic Conference on Sensors and Applications, 1-16th June, Multidisciplinary Digital Publishing Institute, Vol. 1, 2014.
- R.Piyare and S.R.Lee, "Utilizing Smartphone Sensors for Daily Physical Activity Recognition," In Proceedings of The 10th International Conference on Multimedia Information Technology and Applications (MITA 2014), 9th-10th July, Hong Kong University of Science and Technology, Hong Kong, 2014.

- **R.Piyare** and S.R.Lee, "Activity Recognition using Smartphone low level sensor data," 2014 International Conference on Future Information and Communication Engineering (ICFICE 2014), 26th-28th June, Kowloon, Hong Kong, 2014.
- R.Piyare and S.R.Lee, "Mobile Sensing Platform for Personal Health Management," 18th IEEE International Symposium on Consumer Electronics, 22nd-25th June, Jeju, South Korea, 2014.
- **R.Piyare** and S.R.Lee, "Integrating Wireless Sensor Network into Cloud Services for Real-time Data Collection," in ICT Convergence (ICTC), 2013 International Conference on.IEEE, 14th-16th October, Jeju, South Korea, 2013.
- R.Piyare and S.R.Lee, "Smart Home-Control and Monitoring System Using Smart Phone," International Conference, ICCA 2013, Korea University, Seoul Korea, July, 2013.
- **R.Piyare** and M.Tazil, "*Bluetooth Based Home Automation System using Cell Phone*," Presented at 15th IEEE International Symposium on Consumer Electronics, 14th-17th June, Singapore, 2011.
- **R.Piyare** and R.Singh, "Wireless Control of An Automated Guided Vehicle," Presented at 2011 International MultiConference of Engineers and Computer Scientists (IMECS), 16th-18th March, Hong Kong, 2011.

# **Professional Activities**

### **Invited Reviewer:**

- IEEE Transactions on Wireless Communications
- · IEEE Sensors Journal
- · IEEE Access Journal
- · Elsevier Computer Networks Journal
- MDPI Sensors Journal
- MDPI Energy Journal
- MDPI Future Internet Journal
- · IEEE World Forum on Internet of Things (2018, 2019)
- IEEE Global IoT Summit (GIoTS) (2017, 2018)
- 1st Workshop on Internet of Energy Neutral Things (IoENT 2017)
- · 2nd International Conference on Informatics, Robotics, Networks, Control and Systems (IRONCONS 2016)
- NewNets 2019

### **Organization:**

- Web Chair of the 17th ACM/IFIP/USENIX Middleware conference (Middleware 2016)
- Publicity Chair of the 1st Workshop on Internet of Energy Neutral Things (IoENT 2017)

#### Member:

- Institute of Electrical and Electronics Engineers (IEEE)
- International Association of Engineers (IAENG)
- International Association of Computer Science and Informational Technology (IACSIT)

## **Research Artifacts**

Over the course of my research, I have developed various open-source software frameworks for low-power networking and analysis including:

#### WaCo

- An open source Wake-Up Radio COOJA Extension for Simulating Ultra Low Power Radios.
- · https://github.com/waco-sim

#### **KRATOS**

- An open source hardware-software platform for prototyping in LPWANs
- ContikiOS port for Semtech LoRa radio chipset and TI MSP430FR5969 MCU.
- https://contikios4lora.github.io/contikios-lora/

# Certifications.

- 2014 Machine Learning, from Coursera.org
- 2014 The Data Scientist's Toolbox, from Coursera.org
- 2014 More Data Mining with Weka, from The University of Waikato
- 2013 Data Mining with Weka, from The University of Waikato
- 2013 Advanced Protocols for Wireless Ad-hoc Networks, from IEEE
- 2012 Wireless Sensor Networks and Applications, from IEEE
- 2011 Training on Programmable Logic Controllers, from Omron Electronics Limited, Auckland
- 2010 Training on Control and Instrumentation modules, from Feedback Instruments, United Kingdom

# Technical Skills\_

- Programming Languages: C/C++
- IoT Embedded Operating Systems: ContikiOS, TinyOS, TI-RTOS
- · Network simulation: COOJA
- Statistical Analysis Tools: WEKA Data Mining, R, MATLAB
- Familiar with Python, Swift, Apple Xcode, Android Studio, Wireshark
- Intermediate knowledge of Programmable Logic Controller Programming
- Extensive knowledge of MS Office Package, LaTex
- · Operating Systems: Unix/Linux, Windows
- · Version Control Tools: Git, GitHub, GitLab, SVN
- Wireless Technologies: ZigBee, BLE, LoRa, NB-IoT
- IoT Protocols: CTP, RPL, ContikiMAC, CSMA, RIME, 6LoWPAN, UDP, TCP, CoAP, HTTP
- Embedded Platforms: ARM Cortex, PIC, TI MSP430, Atmel AVR, Arduino, Raspberry Pi
- Communication Buses: SPI, I2C, UART, USB

# Referees

Dr. Amy L. Murphy
Energy Efficient Embedded Digital Architectures (E3DA)
Bruno Kessler Foundation (FBK)
Via Sommarive 18, 38050 Povo, TN, Italy
Phone: +39 0461 314 333
Email: murphy@fbk.eu

Dr. Michele Magno Integrated Systems Laboratory (IIS), ETH Zurich Gloriastrasse 35, 8092 Zurich, Switzerland Phone: +41 44 632 66 86

Email: michele.magno@iis.ee.ethz.ch

Dr. Davide Brunelli University of Trento Department of Industrial Engineering Via Sommarive 9, 38123 Povo, TN, Italy

Phone: +39 0461 285221 Email: davide.brunelli@unitn.it